<corpus>
	<document>
		<metadata>
			<source>The Times (London)</source>
			<publication_type>Newspaper</publication_type>
			<year>2020</year>
			<month>February</month>
			<day>15</day>
			<author>Rachel Sylvester; Alice Thomson</author>
			<title>'Brexit is a game-changer … Johnson should prepare for a united Ireland'</title>
			<subtitle>The Sinn Fein leader Mary Lou McDonald says her party's success has implications for the future of the UK, write Rachel Sylvester and Alice Thomson</subtitle>
		</metadata>
		<text length="1678">
			<p>Mary Lou McDonald grew up in a republican household in Dublin to a backdrop of the Troubles in Northern Ireland. "My family's connections with the IRA would have been in the 1920s," she says. But it was the death of the hunger strikers in the Maze prison in 1981, when she was 12, that prompted her own political awakening.</p>
			<p>"For everybody of my age group those moments were absolutely defining, even though you didn't realise it at the time," the Sinn Fein leader says. "There was huge upset across everybody's homes. We all remember asking: why is this happening and who is Margaret Thatcher? There was a profound sense of injustice all across Ireland and in my generation a sense of rage."</p>
			<p>Only 30 years ago Sinn Fein spokesmen were banished from the airwaves in Britain and broadcasters had to use actors to read their words. Now the party has won the most votes in the Irish general election and could be on the verge of going into government. The coalition talks have not yet concluded but it is already clear that Ms McDonald, 50, has broken the two-party stranglehold on Irish politics. The party that was historically the political wing of the IRA has become a power-broker.</p>
			<p>"I am absolutely sure we were elected on a mandate to be in government," she says. "This wasn't a protest vote." Although Sinn Fein did not win the most seats - it fielded only 42 candidates - she insists that it would be "totally wrong" for Fianna Fail and Fine Gael to form a government that excluded her party. "We have to reflect what people are telling us and they are saying they want change."</p>
			<p>Sinn Fein's success has implications not only for Ireland but also for the future of the UK. The election campaign may have been dominated by domestic issues such as housing and health but Ms McDonald insists that people were also voting for a united Ireland. "Certainly, that is in the mix, there is no doubt. Irish unity now is discussed across the island in a way that I never recall in my lifetime. If you look northwards, the unionist majority has gone. There has been a generational turning of the wheel."</p>
			<p>Brexit has changed everything, she says. The Leave vote was driven by "the lowest common denominator of English nationalism" and "you see a society that's hopelessly divided" in Britain. Although the UK's departure from the European Union has not made a unified Ireland inevitable, she thinks Brexit has "accelerated not just the conversation but the immediacy of recognising our collective needs and protecting ourselves".</p>
			<p>Boris Johnson has, she suggests, given a boost to the republican cause with his withdrawal agreement that will create a border in the Irish Sea. "People in the north of Ireland didn't consent to Brexit. It is not their democratic wish, they are being coerced into this position, so I think what he has done and what Brexit has done is to write up in the starkest terms the undemocratic nature of the partition of our island. It leaves the population, the economy, the provision of services entirely at the whim of a Tory government and the Tories have no support in Ireland."</p>
			<p>Under the Good Friday agreement the Northern Ireland secretary has a duty to call a border poll on reunification if there is clear public support. "The polling data demonstrates the trend is only in one direction," Ms McDonald says. "What we need to do now collectively is to start making the preparations for a referendum." She thinks that within five years is a reasonable timeframe but "it could happen in three years". The main thing after a "shambolic" Brexit process is that "we need to be careful that we don't sleepwalk ourselves into potentially a disorderly constitutional change".</p>
			<p>Whatever form the next government takes in Ireland, "the preparation for that poll, and for that constitutional change, needs to start. It is just so utterly reckless for anybody to suggest that you bury your head in the sand as though Brexit hasn't happened and won't have long-term consequences. This isn't a one-off event, this is a gamechanger. I think we have to prepare and I think London has to prepare".</p>
			<p>The prime minister celebrates "the awesome foursome that are incarnated in that red, white and blue flag" but Ms McDonald says that Mr Johnson could be the leader who presides over the break up of the union. The English wouldn't mind losing Northern Ireland in any case, she suggests. "If you said to them, so why is there a border on the island of Ireland? I imagine the vast majority of English people would not know. This is a place apart."</p>
			<p>She was dismayed by the sacking of Julian Smith as Northern Ireland secretary this week - particularly the suggestion that No 10 had been perturbed by an element of the Stormont deal that would create a new body to consider murders carried out during the Troubles. "This is a very negative signal to lots of families and communities that have suffered," she says. "It doesn't help if you have such a lack of continuity in terms of the person you're dealing with. I have wondered at times how much British governments or officials actually get it here. They don't live here so [they say] the North [is] as British as Finchley. It's not. When you come into Belfast you are in Ulster, a province on the island of Ireland."</p>
			<p>Northern Ireland gets big subsidies but the Sinn Fein leader insists: "Irish unity can bring massive economic possibilities. The southern economy is not perfect but it is very dynamic; the North by contrast is quite stagnant and it couldn't be anything other than that because it's a totally artificial situation that's been created by partition."</p>
			<p>She is also keen to get Brussels on side. "On the wider issue of Irish unification I do believe that the EU should have a stance on it, in the same way that they have a stance on Cyprus and … recognised the strategic advantage of German reunification. It's not sustainable over the long term to have a European frontier slap in the middle of our little island."</p>
			<p>Sinn Fein supporters celebrated their victory by singing Irish rebel songs but Ms McDonald has succeeded by distancing her party from its paramilitary past. This mother of two, who was educated at private school and read English literature at Trinity College, Dublin, is a contrast to her predecessor Gerry Adams. "I'm a [younger] generation, I'm a woman, I'm a Dubliner. Of course I'm different," she says, admitting that she prefers gin and tonic to Guinness and loves both T S Eliot and W B Yeats. She says that she has "a good relationship" with Arlene Foster, leader of the Democratic Unionist Party, but it cannot have been easy to build up trust. Mrs Foster survived a bomb attack on her school bus and saw her father shot by the IRA. "I have no reason to feel personal guilt for that but I feel an enormous responsibility, and I think and I hope that she feels it too, to make sure that whatever happens … there is no other small child who comes through that kind of trauma."</p>
			<p>She remembers the violence, including attacks such as the Harrods bombing in 1983. "That was the background to our childhood. You couldn't turn on the television [without seeing] every other day some bomb, some shooting, someone hurt, maimed or injured. That was the cycle and the great credit that the previous generation of republicans deserve is that they managed to stop that cycle."</p>
			<p>She was horrified by the killing of the journalist Lyra McKee in April last year by an organisation called the New IRA, and points out that the dissidents have also threatened Sinn Fein politicians. "They have nothing to do with us and the war is over."</p>
			<p>Ms McDonald does not want a return to violence but nor will she disavow the past. "I am who I am, I come from my background and I live in the here and now … It's important that you don't live in the past, that you move on to today and into the future but you have to recognise what happened in the past, you shouldn't run away from that." Including the violence? "Absolutely. Let's be clear here, there was a war on this island and the British state forces were full protagonists. Let's not pretend it was just because people on this island are uniquely dysfunctional … we had a colonial experience."</p>
			<p>Although she did not join Sinn Fein until after the Good Friday agreement, that was "as much coincidence" as a point of principle. "I don't agree with violence," she says but "there was a conflict on. Nelson Mandela was famously characterised by Margaret Thatcher as a terrorist because [the ANC] took armed actions. You can't take it in isolation, you have to understand why. People don't for no good reason take up arms, you have to honestly understand and unpack the politics if you want to make peace."</p>
			<p>Her children are 16 and 13. She must worry that any destabilisation in Northern Ireland could see a return to violence. "I'm not filled with terror, I'm filled with hope and absolute determination. We want to strike now for our freedom peacefully and democratically and we want our friends in England and Scotland and Wales to help us on that journey."</p>
			<p>Mary Louise McDonald</p>
			<p>Curriculum vitae</p>
			<p>Born May 1, 1969 Educated Notre Dame Des Missions, Churchtown; Trinity College, Dublin. Career She was a consultant for the Irish Productivity Centre, researcher for the Institute of European Affairs and worked in the Educational and Training Services Trust before being elected to the European parliament in 2004. Became Sinn Fein's vice-president in 2009 and a TD for Dublin Central in 2011. President of Sinn Fein since February 2018. Family Married to Martin Lanigan, a gas control superintendent; two teenage children.</p>
			<p>Quick fire</p>
			<p>WB Yeats or TS Eliot? I love both but if I have to choose, TS Eliot Nelson Mandela or Mahatma Gandhi? It has to be Nelson Mandela Guinness or gin and tonic? Gin and tonic. I hate Guinness Ryanair or BA? Ryanair Brussels or Belfast? Belfast The Ferryman or Waiting for Godot? Waiting for Godot Parasite or 1917? I haven't seen either Derry Girls, left, or Succession? Derry Girls PJ Masks or The Avengers? The Avengers, but my superhero of choice is Wonder Woman</p>
			<p>Graphic</p>
			<p>Mary Lou McDonald believes the previous generation of republican politicians, including Gerry Adams, deserve credit for stopping the cycle of violence in IrelandCRISPIN RODWELL FOR THE TIMES</p>
		</text>
	</document>
	<document>
		<metadata>
			<source>The Guardian - Final Edition</source>
			<publication_type>Newspaper</publication_type>
			<year>2010</year>
			<month>February</month>
			<day>24</day>
			<author>Philip Hoare</author>
			<title>G2: Big, big trouble: The 100-tonne fin whale washed up this week in Cornwall has caused a stink for locals as it rots on the beach. So how can they shift it? Whale expert Philip Hoare explains - Correction Appended</title>
			<subtitle></subtitle>
		</metadata>
		<text length="853">
			<p>Of all the deputations from the deep, a beached whale is the most astounding. Not just because of its size, but also because of the terrors it holds for the humans who may confront it. A stranded whale was once regarded as an ill omen; a right whale that stranded in the Thames in 1658 was widely seen as an augury of the death of Oliver Cromwell. Even now, the arrival this week of a 100-tonne, 56ft (16.9m) fin whale on Portowan Beach in Cornwall is a remarkable phenomenon - not least because Balaenoptera physalus is second only to the blue whale in size, reaching up to 85ft in length.</p>
			<p>It belongs to the family of rorqual whales, so-called for the pleated ridges (from the Norwegian for furrow) that line their bellies. Foraging entirely on small fish, fin whales take great gulps of sea water to trap their prey, expanding their stomachs like concertinas and filtering their food through plates of baleen in their mouths (the whalebone once prized by corset-makers). Fin whales are unique among whales in being assymmetrically marked: the righthand side of their lower parts is a soft, dove-like grey; the left, much darker. Scientists hypothesise that the whales use this pale side to "flash" their prey and herd them into place.</p>
			<p>I've seen these animals many times off Provincetown, Cape Cod: to have one swim under the boat is a deeply strange feeling. Diving below, the creature never seems to end, until it emerges at the other side with an explosive whoosh! from its twin blowholes. Watching its sleek dorsal fin scythe through the water, I'm always reminded that fin whales are the fastest of all great whales, dubbed the greyhounds of the sea and able to swim at 24 knots an hour.</p>
			<p>Too fast for 19th-century hunters of Herman Melville's era; only with the invention of the grenade harpoon did these speedy cetaceans (the name for this suborder) come within reach. The 20th century saw an unprecedented cull of rorqual whales in the Southern Ocean, by factory ships from the Falklands and South Georgia, as well as Norwegian, Soviet and Japanese fleets. And fin whales suffered the worst casualties of all: 720,000 were killed in the Southern Hemisphere alone.</p>
			<p>This particular animal probably died as a result of a shipstrike in the Bay of Biscay - where lucky ferry passengers may occasionally see these leviathans swimming across the bows. The skeleton of one such casualty, found in Andalucia, was used by the contemporary Mexican artist Gabriel Orozoco in an installation in London's White Cube gallery in 2006. The Cornish whale, however, has drifted into royal hands. Extraordinarily, a still extant 14th-century edict determines that any whale, dolphin, sturgeon or porpoise washed on to English shores is the property of the monarch, a relic of an age when a whale represented great wealth.</p>
			<p>Since whales are of little use to Buckingham Palace these days, that responsibility now devolves to the Receiver of Wreck, Alison Kentuck. From her office in Southampton, Kentuck tells me that the whale, a female, had been seen floating at sea for a day or so, and is now in a rocky, inaccessible cove. "We're waiting for a predicated storm to come along and wash it along to somewhere where it will be easier to deal with," she says. "It's already quite badly decayed - apparently you can smell it from the clifftop. Although since it's now on Duchy of Cornwall land, it's actually the property of the Prince of Wales - or perhaps that should be the Prince of Whales?"</p>
			<p>Apart from cracking bad jokes, one of Kentuck's tasks is to prevent public interaction with beached whales. The carcasses can communicate zoonotic, or inter-species disease (as can live whales, a warning for anyone within spouting distance of a cetacean), or worse. The buildup of gases in an animal's stomach can cause a whale to expand to bursting point - in 1617, a sperm whale beached at Scheveningen in the Netherlands exploded, fatally infecting bystanders. Indeed, the artist Albrecht Durer, in his eagerness to reach a similarly stranded whale on Denmark's Zealand coast, caught a fever from the marsh, and likewise perished as a result. It seems that in the case of the whale, the meeting of human history and natural history is seldom a happy one.</p>
			<p>Kentuck's first duty is to offer a beached whale to the Natural History Museum; a necropsy may be carried out by the Zoological Society of London. But generally, the animal is destined for the dump. In the past, Kentuck has ordered plant machinery to tear the carcasses into manageable chunks before disposal in a local landfill. It is an ignominous end for such an exquisite creature; but perhaps a better fate than that facing its cousins in the Southern Ocean where, under the guise of "scientific research", a Japanese whaling fleet is even now harpooning fin whales destined not for the laboratory, but for the supermarket counter.</p>
			<p>Philip Hoare's Leviathan or The Whale is published by Fourth Estate. To order a copy for £8.99 with free UK p&p go to guardian.co.uk/bookshop or call 0330 333 6846</p>
			<p>Captions:</p>
			<p>The 56ft fin whale stranded on Portowan beach in Cornwall.</p>
			<p>Photograph: Apex News</p>
			<p>Correction</p>
			<p>* The fin whale was said to be able to swim at 24 knots an hour (Big, big trouble, 24 February, page 10, G2). Numerous readers wrote to point out that a knot - ie, a nautical mile per hour - is a measure of acceleration. We should just have said that the fin whale can swim at 24 knots.</p>
			<p>Correction-Date: February 25, 2010 Thursday</p>
		</text>
	</document>
	<document>
		<metadata>
			<source>The Independent (London)</source>
			<publication_type></publication_type>
			<year>2000</year>
			<month>February</month>
			<day>21</day>
			<author>John Lichfield</author>
			<title>THE MANY FACES OF JOAN OF ARC</title>
			<subtitle>THE MAID OF ORLEANS HAS BEEN ADOPTED AS A CHAMPION OF THE LEFT, THE RIGHT AND THE FEMINIST MOVEMENT. NOW A NEW FILM ATTEMPTS TO REDEFINE HER AGAIN. SINNER, SAINT OR REVOLUTIONARY - WILL THE REAL JOAN PLEASE STAND UP? BY JOHN LICHFIELD</subtitle>
		</metadata>
		<text length="1597">
			<p>Her name was Jehanne or Jeannette or Jeanne D'Arc or Darc. In her own eastern French di alect, she would have called herself something like "Shann Day". In her many letters - written for her, because she was illiterate - she signed herself, portentously, "Jehanne La Pucelle" (Jeanne the Virgin). We call her "Joan", following Shakespeare and the English medieval chroniclers, who portray her as a calculating witch and a bastard daughter of French royalty.</p>
			<p>Luc Besson's movie, Jeanne d'Arc, which opens in Britain next month, is the 31st film about Jeanne or Joan. The first of them was made in 1900 - the Hundred Years War has now lasted as long in the cinema as it did in real life.</p>
			<p>Why this modern obsession with Jeanne? She was virtually forgotten by the French themselves for 400 years, until she was re-invented as first a patriotic-republican, and then, in the mid-19th century, as a religious- conservative heroine.</p>
			<p>In the United States and Canada, she has become a feminist icon. In Latin America, she is now claimed by the Left as one of the first popular, resistance leaders: a female Che in chain mail. In France, she has been kidnapped and idolised by Jean-Marie Le Pen's xenophobic far right. (They love the fact that she was a pious scourge of foreigners; and, even more, the fact that she was betrayed by her own countrymen.) For many young French people, therefore, Jeanne's shining armour has become tarnished by association with neo-fascism.</p>
			<p>The movie, if it does nothing else, may rescue her from that undeserved fate. Olivier Bouzy, deputy director of the Jeanne d'Arc study centre in Orleans, reports an abrupt surge of interest in Jeanne among young French people since the film opened in France last autumn. "For the first time, she has been presented to them as a character that they can sympathise with, not a symbol of anything, but a real person," he says.</p>
			<p>Besson's film appeals to the young because it portrays her as one of them: a brilliant but disturbed teenager. (Jeanne was 19 when she was burned at the stake in Rouen on 31 May 1431, after a military-political career lasting just over two years.) The result is a movie with extraordinary lurches of style and tone, with successive scenes reminiscent of The Shining, Braveheart and Buffy the Vampire Slayer.</p>
			<p>At one stage Jeanne casually asks a minion, as though asking for alight for a cigarette, "Raymond, will you take that arrow out of my leg?".</p>
			<p>Even more oddly, Besson's movie has just been voted the best "French" film of 1999, which shows that Jeanne's power to create myths and confusion is undiminished.</p>
			<p>The movie may have a French director (the most American of French directors) but it is, by all the usual definitions, an American film, produced in Hollywood, partly with French money, shot in the Czech Republic and acted in English. None of the main characters is played by a French actor.</p>
			<p>Besson says his movie cuts through the myths to present the "real Jeanne". In passing, it reinforces several myths and invents a couple of new ones (suggesting for instance that she was driven by pathological hatred of the English because they raped and murdered her sister).</p>
			<p>So who was the real Jeanne? The simple facts are well-known (and broadly followed by the Besson movie). A peasant girl came from nowhere, directed by "voices" of saints, to lead the French armies and defeat the English. She lifted a cruel siege of Orleans; created a sense of French nationhood; changed the course of the Hundred Years War; and was burned by the English as a heretic and a witch.</p>
			<p>The problem is that, according to her most recent, French biographer, Roger Caratini, little of that is true: it is based on fanciful, romantic and cynically politicised versions of her life, invented in the late 19th century. The "real" Jeanne came from nowhere, but she never really led the French armies. There was no siege of Orleans. She never truly defeated the English and, in any case, her enemies were as much French as English in what was a Balkanesque, three-way civil war. Joan's brief career had great, temporary impact, but probably changed the course of nothing.</p>
			<p>It is true that the foundations of the French state were laid by King Charles VII - the man she helped to have crowned. Charles accomplished this feat after cruelly (and sensibly) dismissing her to make deals with the Burgundian forces that Jeanne hated as much as the English. Finally, her trial and execution - though approved and paid for by the English - were mostly driven by extreme repressive and conservative forces in the French Catholic church, led by the University of Paris.</p>
			<p>All the more curious, therefore, that Jeanne should have been canonised by Rome in 1920, 500 years after her death. She remains the only Catholic saint ever to have been burned as a heretic. The file on her in the Vatican remains adamantly, and inexplicably, closed.</p>
			<p>There is no shortage of other sources of information. There is probably more contemporary written material on Jeanne than any other medieval figure. Much of it comes from the records of her trial, and the posthumous "appeal" and commissions of inquiry set up by Charles VII 25 years later to clear her name (and his conscience).</p>
			<p>From the trial minutes, and her letters, Jeanne's personality and voice have survived the centuries: calm, obstinate, driven but not really the voice of a deranged fanatic (which is how the movie, finally, presents her). We also learn, among other things, that she was a wonderful cook and a good-looking woman with large breasts.</p>
			<p>From the age of 13, Jeanne heard the voices of saints telling her that it was her destiny to help the dauphin Charles to become king and defeat the rival claim of the infant King Henry VI of England.</p>
			<p>The "English" king was widely accepted in northern and south western France. The Duke of Burgundy, who controlled eastern France and Flanders, supported the English, but occasionally changed sides.</p>
			<p>The dauphin Charles had been regularly defeated in battle and seemed a lost cause.</p>
			<p>In February 1429, when she was 17 years old, Jeanne was finally brought to meet the dauphin. She told him that God had appointed her to lift the English "siege" of Orleans and have him crowned king in Reims. He sent her to Orleans, Mr Caratini points out, as part of a food convoy, not as the head of an army. There, she galvanised the city's defenders (under no real threat from a relatively small English force) to assault a few English outposts. This they did successfully and the main English army then retreated, for reasons still unknown (perhaps startled by the sight of a woman in armour).</p>
			<p>Jeanne had played no great part in the skirmishes, but she became a great heroine and mascot for Charles' previously demoralised forces, who won a couple of more serious battles against their English/French enemies.</p>
			<p>Charles was anointed king and then, on Jeanne's naive urging, marched on pro -"English" Paris and was utterly routed.</p>
			<p>From then on, Charles VII rejected Jeanne's messianic zeal to "boot out the English" and pursued diplomatic solutions.</p>
			<p>Disgusted, she fought a brief and unsuccessful guerrilla war, with a small band of devotees. She was captured by the Burgundians outside Compiegne on 29 May, 1430. Her active career had lasted for just over a year.</p>
			<p>King Charles ungratefully refused to ransom her. The English paid pounds 10,000 and handed her to the church, which strongly disapproved of peasant girls who spoke to saints.</p>
			<p>After a lengthy trial, in which Jeanne defended herself with great intelligence and dignity, she was condemned for heresy and witchcraft (in part for having worn men's clothes). She recanted, to avoid the stake, but a few days later was "found" in her cell dressed as a man.</p>
			<p>For having "relapsed", she was burnt alive. This was almost certainly a medieval sting operation. According to some historians - and the Besson movie - her women's clothes were taken away. She had to dress as a man or go naked.</p>
			<p>There is no evidence for this accusation, but the men's clothes were certainly placed in her cell to tempt her, probably by her French inquisitors. The English were content to leave her in jail, Caratini says.</p>
			<p>What to make of Jeanne finally? She was plainly a creature of her times: a 15th century in which piety and brutality, superstition and chivalry, went hand-in-hand; when people, recovering from the black death, beset by terrible civil and foreign wars, saw signs and omens everywhere, without being sure whether they came from God or from Satan.</p>
			<p>Jeanne also transcends her times: she is both medieval and oddly modern. This is not just because she abandoned the "decent reserve of her sex" (as her condemnation put it).</p>
			<p>The late 14th and early 15th centuries abound with female seers and prophets. A Flemish heroine led her people in battle against the French 40 years earlier (and was promptly killed). Jeanne herself met another French prophetess and instructed her to "go home and look after your husband and children".</p>
			<p>Jeanne stands out because of the extraordinary energy, mental strength and inner confidence that she, an illiterate teenager, displayed in pursuing her quest and in standing up to a group of crafty and malevolent inquisitors. To that extent, she has sometimes been seen (despite her belated Catholic sainthood) as one of the forerunners of the Reformation in the next century.</p>
			<p>It is possible to dismiss Jeanne as a medieval fanatic. It is also possible to recognise in her the stirrings of belief in the individual conscience: one of the building blocks of Western modernity.</p>
			<p>Graphic</p>
			<p>Then and now: Joan of Arc as portrayed in a 15th-century manuscript, above, and the modern view of Joan, top left, as portrayed by; Milla Jovovich in Luc Besson's forthcoming film 'Jeanne D'Arc' Bridgeman; Art Library</p>
		</text>
	</document>
</corpus>